Good evening everyone.
I'll now call to order this uh September
23rd meeting of Lancaster City Council.
A few uh reminders at the top of our
meeting. Uh this meeting and its
participants are being recorded this
evening. Please take a moment to silence
your phones and devices if you haven't
done so already. Uh one uh note on the
agenda, bill six that was scheduled for
a first reading this evening will not be
discussed. It will has been moved to the
first meeting in October. During this
meeting, there will be opportunities for
public comment. The first general public
comment period is open for residents who
registered in advance of the meeting to
speak about items uh that are not on the
agenda. Residents may also comment on
individual items on our agenda in the
legislative section which is section
nine. Finally, a second public comment
period will be at the end of this
meeting. Uh for any other speakers
wishing to address council for all
speakers, no matter in which portion of
the agenda, uh please begin with your
name and block of residence for our
meeting record. Be advised that public
comment is not necessarily a question
and answer period. All comments are
limited to three minutes per speaker.
And to keep time, I have this light in
front of me. It will turn green when a
speaker begins. It will turn yellow. It
will blink yellow when there is one
minute remaining and blink red when
three minutes has been exhausted. I
appreciate everyone's cooperation in
advance in ensuring that we all have
equal time.
Uh last but not least, speakers
addressing city council and the members
of this audience will be expected to
conduct themselves in an orderly manner
and remain respectful to others. Thank
you. Now, for all of those who are
willing and able, please rise for the
pledge of
>> allegiance
to the flag
of
the stand.
>> Mr. Harris, would you please call the
role of members?
>> Yes, Madam President.
Mr. Matt
>> here.
>> Mr. Roya
>> Mr. Cle
>> here.
>> Miss Craig
>> Miss Diaz
>> here.
>> Mr. H.
>> And President B
>> here. Council Hirs is excused this
evening.
>> We'll now move to the approval of the
minutes of the September 9th meeting of
city council.
>> Motion to approve.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion and a second for our
meeting minutes. Counselors, any
comments on them?
Hearing
none. Mr. Harris,
>> Mr. Matt,
>> I.
>> Mr. Roya,
>> Mr. Cle,
>> I.
>> M. Craig.
>> Miss Diaz.
>> I.
>> And President Ba.
We'll now move to proclamations, honors,
awards, and resolutions of recognition
of of which we have one uh this evening.
Is that right, Mr. Harris?
>> Yes, Madam President. We do. We have the
uh the Governor's Hispanic Heritage
Month proclamation.
>> Thank you very much, counselors. This
evening we're joined by uh Jose A. Nunes
Ruiz who is a commissioner for Lancaster
County on the governor's advisory
commission on Latino affairs. He's uh
wanted to come here this evening to read
us the proclamation signed by Governor
Shapiro recognizing Hispanic Heritage
Month. Uh if you would like to come
forward, Jose, thank you so much for
being here. Um, I know that you may have
some words that you would like to share
and then uh you'll be reading the
content of the resolution in Spanish for
us this evening.
>> You got it.
>> Good evening to all to city council to
mayor source and to the public today.
I'm a proud resident of the city of
Lancaster. I live on the 100 block of
South Queen Street. So, I'm very proud
to be part of this. I consider myself an
Amishan and also be proud to represent
our county in the governor's advisory
commission on Latino affairs. So today I
bring you like I said the proclamation
on behalf of our governor the honorable
Josh Pero and our executive director org
who is the director of the commission
and the plation reads as follow. I will
be doing the plation in Spanish. Hope
you Thank you.
[Music]
Latino
Medicio
technolog
Latino
groupto
latinos
and confl.
[Music]
Latino,
Pennsylvania.
Financial
Joe Peril, Pennsylvania.
Latino.
That is a message from our governor and
and and the in the second spoken
language which is Spanish in in in our
commonwealth. So I want I want to thank
you for the opportunity for letting me
read this and especially this is my
first time reading in Spanish. So but my
second time reading Spanish but my first
time reading here in Spanish. So, thank
you very much. And like I said, let's
not forget that Latinos and Lat Hispanos
and Latino Americano are always we're
growing 1.2 million and that that that
growth will continue in Lancaster
County. So many Latino leaders have come
from here. So, I am proud to be a Puerto
Rican. I am proud to be a Lancastrian
and I always and like I always say when
I travel throughout the state or
anywhere, I'm a proud Amish Rican. So,
thank you for the opportunity and
>> thank you.
[Applause]
I appreciate you being here this
evening, Jose. Uh, we, as you may
recall, counselors and members of the
public, uh, passed our resolution
honoring Hispanic Heritage Month at our
last meeting. Um, and I will mention
that we are having a celebration for
Hispanic Heritage Month on October 4th
in Ule Plaza from 2 to 8:00 PM featuring
dancers, entertainers, uh, awards
ceremony, food and drink, vendors, and
so much fun. So, please come out and
join us to celebrate that in the city.
Um, before you uh you go away from from
your seat there, counselors, do you have
any additional comments uh questions uh
for Jose?
Thank you for being here so much on this
rainy evening. Thank you.
That will take us uh to our first public
comment period and thank you for leaving
that with the city clerk. Uh this uh
comment period again is reserved for
residents uh who have contacted the city
clerk prior to this meeting uh to
request the opportunity to address city
council. Uh Mr. Mr. Harris, do we have
any commenters for this first period?
>> We do not, Madam President.
>> Thank you very much. We will then move
to our next item on the agenda, which is
reports requested by council, confirming
that we have none of those this evening.
Is that right, Mr. Harris?
>> Um, we do have a report requested by
council this evening. That would be the
may the mayor's budget address.
>> I apologize. I was I was incorrect. Um,
so this evening we do have a report
request by council uh because of the new
timeline uh set forth in our new
charter. We can say new until the end of
this year and then it's not new anymore
I guess. Um we will be receiving our uh
mayor's budget address this evening.
Mayor Sarra.
>> Uh thank you council president. Um would
you mind taking one of these?
>> It is September 23rd and I'm introducing
the 2026 budget. This may be the
earliest that any mayor in recent
history has introduced a budget and it
is one of the many changes brought by
the adoption of the home roll charter
last year approved by 68% of the voters
of Lancaster. The home rule charter has
institutionalized a set of best
management practices that really define
my administration strategic priority of
sound government. With home rule,
council and the public not only have a
budget introduced earlier than before,
but also a comprehensive capital plan
encompassing the general fund and each
of the utilities. Council has been
engaged in a review of the capital plan
for several months and will be voting on
the capital plan later this evening.
In addition, a new controller with
additional responsibilities and input
into the city's accounting practices,
financial policies, and budgeting will
be elected on November 4th alongside a
new mayor and council majority. Plus,
the administrative code under review by
council now contemplates a set of
financial policies, including an
official fund balance policy, investment
p policy, and debt policy, further
institutionalizing best practices.
Perhaps most notably, the home roll
charter allows us to move away from a
cycle of regular property tax increases
by adjusting the earned income tax. This
was done last year and as a result, we
are projecting an 11% increase in earned
income tax revenues in 2026.
Finally, relative to this budget
message, the home roll charter also lays
out what my message should include. So,
let's get those portions out of the way.
In the 2026 general fund, we are
projecting 81.8 million in revenues and
81.7 million in expenses. No property
tax or earned income tax increase is
proposed.
I'm going to say that again, you guys.
That's cause for celebration. No
property tax or earned income tax
increase is proposed. On the revenue
side, overall income is projected to
rise just 2% which is actually a bit
higher than we anticipated given that
this is the first budget without
American Rescue Plan fund, Rescue Plan
Act funds. There are a couple of other
bright spots including increases in
investment earnings and permit fees
which I'll come back to. On the expense
side, there is a projected increase of
6% which is 2% higher than our goal of
4% due to a variety of factors including
health insurance up 5% and staffing
including the restoration of a chief of
staff position for the incoming
administration, the filling of vacant
positions and the addition of a few new
positions. Additionally, we have been
making adjustments to salary allocations
between the general fund and utilities.
As you are aware, we have positions
whose job responsibilities are split
between the general fund and utilities.
Approximately 36 $360,000
has been moved from various utilities
back to the general fund, primarily
impacting the Department of Public
Works. Within the enterprise funds,
there are no proposed increases in trash
and recycling, storm water, sewer, or
water for inside customers.
Pretty good. However, next week we are
filing a rate case before the public
utility commission to raise water rates
for outside city customers. We expect,
let me just say again, those are outside
city customers. We're going to the PUC.
We expect these rates to go into effect
into mid2026.
I also want to highlight our general
fund reserve. In 2025, we projected
adding $2.4 million to the general
reserve fund.
However, because of increases in earned
income tax and permitting revenues, not
including the 7.8 8 million in building
permit revenues related to the Carissa
project. We anticipate this year with
4.7 million in addition additional
revenue. We are requesting that 1
million be allocated to the 2026 budget.
This still provides a fund balance
contribution of 3.7 million and will
increase our fund balance percent from
17 to 22 which is aligned with the
proposed fund balance policy that is in
the administrative code presently being
contemplated by council. The $7.8
million generated from the Carissa
project at 260 Greenfield Road is a
total outlier. In consultation with our
auditor, this will be treated similar to
a grant, meaning it is not showing in
the revenues or expenses related to the
budget. A separate report will be
provided to council outlining that
revenue and all the expenses that are
related to the data center. Council will
have some decisions to make related to
the utilizations of utilization of these
funds for which I will be preparing a
separate mo memo for your consideration.
Number two, there are no significant
changes to the work of the city included
in this budget. However, I do want to
call your attention to one area of our
operations that you will be hearing more
about during the department budget
presentations, and that is permitting.
On average, the city receives
approximately 3,000 permits annually,
80% of which are building permits.
Permitting is a complicated government
function with multiple city departments
providing review and has been a source
of ongoing frustration both internally
and externally. We've been listening and
as I reported to council last month, we
have been making progress and there is
much more work to do to make it faster,
clearer, and fully online. This budget
proposes additional investments in
centralizing the permitting within
administrative services since nearly
every department has a permitting role.
You'll hear more details in the
department budget presentations. I want
to emphasize that while this area
requires additional improvements, we are
offsetting added costs by being more
strategic about what kind of work is
outsourced. In turn, this is generating
the additional revenue to support those
costs.
Number three, while we usually only
discuss the city's debt position when we
are soliciting a bond, this is a good
moment to note progress. Earlier in my
tenure, the city's credit outlook had
been downgraded by Moody's to a negative
outlook, then neutral, and now we are
positive in large measure because we
demonstrated our willingness to
strengthen our financial position by
moving to home rule and increasing our
earned income tax. Number four,
additional information regarding the
budget will be presented at the October
6 council committee meeting along with a
detailed line item budget followed by
two rounds of department budget
presentations. The first set of
department budget presentations will be
on Tuesday, October 21st, and the second
will be on Tuesday, November the 18th.
These sessions replace the allday
Saturday session traditionally held in
December.
And finally, as I prepared this this
budget address, my last one, I revisited
Mayor Gray's final budget message
delivered in 2017. He noted that over
his 12 years, a priority was restoring
the city's fiscal stability. Through
practices that his administration put in
place, a $69 million deficit by 2012 was
averted. Over the last eight years, we
have built on this foundation and I'm
pleased to say that with the passage of
home rule, we have eliminated our
structural deficit. It is a really big
deal.
However, continued fiscal restraint and
a continued strong economy are both
necessary for the city's long-term
financial health. A downturn in either
will have consequences, which is why I
urge future administrations and councils
to continue holding the line on spending
and tax increases.
Finally, I want to thank the staff who
have been working on the budget for
months, especially the accounting team
under Director Campbell's leadership.
Thank you, Tina.
This has been this is truly a team
effort and has been one of the smoothest
budget processes, especially given that
is being delivered months earlier. I
look forward to continued conversation
in the months ahead and thank you
council for the opportunity to present
my final did I say final enough? Budget
message.
>> Thank you very much, Mayor Sarra.
council looks forward to receiving the
budget on October 6 um and hearing our
initial presentation at that uh meeting
of committees of council. So, thank you.
Um I'll also note that generally
practice has been that when council
receives it, it's also available online
to the public. So, that's the full line
item budget um on the administrative
services website. I'm assuming generally
where is found. Thank you very much.
>> Thank you. Our next item on the agenda
this evening is interim reports of
committees of council. I think I'm
correct in saying we have none of those
tonight, Mr. Harris. Is that right?
>> Thank you. We'll now move into our
legislative agenda this evening. We
begin with items for the Heritage
Conservation District.
Mr. Harris, if you would.
>> Yes, Madam President. Considering the
following applications and
recommendations from the Historical
Commission for improvements to
properties within the Heritage
Conservation District. Uh,
Sunkartto Holdings LLC, owner of 250
Harrisburg Avenue, proposes construction
of a new elevator tower and a steel
carport with an upper level deck on the
east elevation of a converted brick
warehouse.
And the second is 2011 West King Street
LLC owner owner and Benjamin A. Samberg
Arct architect proposed construction of
a new concrete entry steps and a rear
rooftop deck. Uh these applications were
recommended for approval by the
historical commission.
>> Thank you very much, Mr. Harris. We have
a motion on these.
>> Motion to approve. Second.
>> We have a motion on a second. Council
Craig, um just confirming your uh motion
is to approve uh items A, B, and C. Is
that correct?
>> A and B.
>> There's no C. Just A and B.
>> I'm sorry. Maybe I'm I'm operating under
an older
>> There are two on the uh two A and B and
B.
>> A and B.
>> Yes.
>> Thank you very much.
>> Yeah, there's nothing to add more than
what is here. A motion to approve for
both.
>> For both. Okay. Thank you very much. We
have a motion uh and a second for
approval of those two items on the
agenda this evening. Are there any uh
representatives from the applicants uh
here this evening or any members of the
public um or I'm sorry any any
representatives of the applicants here
this evening?
>> Are there any comments from council
from the public on the items
hearing? None. Mr. Harris,
>> Mr. Mant.
>> Mr. Royal
>> I.
>> Mr. Cle
>> I. Miss Craig
>> I.
>> Miss Diaz
>> President Baker
>> I.
>> Next item on our legislative agenda item
B. These are ordinances for final
passage. We have administration bill
number 7 2025. Mr. Harris. An ordinance
of the council of the city of Lancaster,
county of Lancaster, Commonwealth of
Pennsylvania, adopting a five-year
capital plan for the fiscal years 2026
to 2030. A program providing for the
proper acquisition, repair, and
provision for the necessary equipment
and infrastructure for the effective and
efficient delivery of public services,
including projects resulting in the
additions, replacements, or changes to
city facilities.
infrastructure and equipment, allowing
for a severance provision, providing for
the repeal of inconsistent ordinances,
and providing for an effective date.
>> Motion to approve.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion and a second. Council
Royal.
>> Thank you, Council President. I don't
have anything additional to add. We uh
sat through two hearings uh with
Director Campbell and Director Campbell
um who gave an extensive presentation on
the capital budget. uh just want to
extend my gratitude to uh both director
Campbell's on uh pro providing uh our
first ever capital budget.
>> Yes, sir.
>> Thank you very much. I've had the
opportunity to meet uh with people about
various topics and inevitably it comes
up the fact that uh one of the hallmarks
of good government is planning and we
are in this rare but amazing position to
have a capital budget in front of us and
that's not a thing that a lot of cities
can say. Um, so I'm incredibly proud of
that and also want to thank uh director
Tina Campbell and Stephen Campbell uh
particularly for their work in putting
this together. Any additional comments
uh from council?
>> I also wanted to thank uh director Tina
Campbell as well as the department of
public works led by director Steven
Campbell. I was very impressed with the
planning that went into the capital plan
and making sure it had a low budgetary
impact um for future projections and I
look forward to over the next years uh
revisiting it and making sure that we
have sound planning and uh we couldn't
have done it without the leadership from
both uh director Campbell. So I wanted
to take a moment and thank them both.
>> Thank you councelor Med. Any additional
council comments?
Comments from the public on the bill
>> hearing. None. Mr. Harris.
>> Mr. Med.
>> I.
>> Mr. Royal.
>> Mr. Cles.
>> I.
>> Miss. Craig.
>> Miss. Diaz.
>> I.
>> And President Baker.
We have capital budget. Yay. That's a
big deal. If you're a nerd, it's a big
deal.
Uh, the next the next item. Yes. Thank
you.
We we got there.
Uh the next item on our agenda would
have been bill six, but as I made
mention at the top of the meeting, uh
that will be introduced at our next
regular meeting of council in October.
So we'll move to item D, which is
resolutions, uh of which we have one
this evening, uh resolution number 63
2025, Mr. Harris,
>> a resolution of the Council of the City
of Lancaster authorizing the filing of
the Commonwealth Finance Authority local
share account application for funding in
the amount not to exceed $1 million for
HDC's Mid-Atlantic Apartments at College
Avenue 3.
>> Motion to approve.
>> Second.
>> Have a motion and a second. Councelor
Craig.
>> Thank you, Council President. Um the um
local shares account grant comes from
the state which are are gaming funds but
must come to the m municipality
and in this case the city is the
municipality and then that passes on the
funds to the subgrantee
and uh my understanding is that there is
someone here from mid-Atlantic please
come forward.
>> Thank you.
Yes, tonight we're hearing a
presentation from HTC Mid Mid-Atlantic
counselors. You have a copy of this
presentation so you're able to bring it
up in front of you. Welcome. Thank you
for being here. And just Yeah, there you
go. You got it.
Okay, I think I hear it. My
>> You got it. Yeah. Okay. Thanks. Uh good
evening. My name is Kim Crowder and I
have the pleasure of being the uh senior
vice president of real estate
development for HDC Mid-Atlantic. And so
I just want to take a couple minutes to
give you a little bit of an update of
what we have going on uh over at College
A since there's there's quite a bit of
uh work happening over there. Um and so
if you have your um presentation, if you
want to flip to the next page, um this
shows all three phases. Um phase one is
64 units and um was completed recently
and we'll I'll go into a little bit more
detail here. um the DELP wing um which
will be phase two uh is currently in at
PHFA right now for low-income housing
tax credits. Um and then what we came to
talk about tonight is Marietta phase
three which we anticipate would be about
48 units give or take. Um so that's the
master plan for what we have going on
over at College AB. So we can skip to
the next one. Thank you so much. So this
is the building that just opened
recently. Um, and as I said, I'm not
going to give you every piece of
information here, but you know, try to
give you what I think are the most
important pieces. Um, and I've been
doing this for a long time. Um, I've
been in affordable housing for over 20
years, and Oops. And I can tell you that
I've never seen this happen before. when
we opened our door for applications um
at our offices over on King Street um at
8:00 in the morning on Saturday, April
1st, uh there was a line out the door
and down the street for people for
applications. So within the first 30
days, we received over 500 applications
for 64 apartments. Um and we were the
wait list was closed at the end of
April. We had so many applications that
we wouldn't be able to process them. And
so I'm very pleased to tell you that by
the end of June of this year, we were
full. Um we have all leased every
apartment in the building. Um and we
continue to have a 3 to fiveyear waiting
list uh for those apartments. And so I
think it just underscores the need uh in
the area. Um and why we're really
excited and motivated about doing phase
two um and then also phase three. Um we
can go to the next one now. Um, this is
just super quick to take you through the
apartments. Um, if you've driven by on
College A, the outside is lovely. Um,
all the landscaping is in. Um, 64
apartments. We have a mix of one and two
bedrooms. Um, and the rents range from
$228 to $950 per month, uh, depending on
the unit size and income level. Um, and
the other thing that I would point out
is that something that is really
important to HDC is that we don't just
provide housing. Uh we make sure that we
provide resident services uh on our
campuses. And so um we have resident
services um on this campus um 13 hours a
week and that will be available for
residents to help connect them to other
resources within the community to make
sure that they uh are successful in the
apartment. Um and this particular
building also has a set aside for adults
with disabilities. And so if you come to
visit us, you'll see that um the
community is completely accessible. Um
and we are really excited that we were
able to partner with UDS on phase one.
Okay, we can skip. Here's a couple of
the community spaces. Um you can see
some of these from outside as you're
walking by. Um on the left is our
community room. Uh we were able to I I
think one of the things that's really
interesting about the site is it was a
really small site and we were able to
fit 64 apartments there and also carve
out a little space outside for some of
the children that live in the building.
And so we have this really great uh
playground area that's on the site um
and kind of protected to it sits kind of
in a little uh courtyard uh on the
campus. And so we're really excited
about that. Uh, and then one of the
other things that we added is um some of
these little I call them vignettes,
these little seating areas uh for folks
to be able to go to if they want to get
outside of their apartment and don't
really want to go to the full community
room. And most of these are located
outside of the laundry rooms which are
located on every floor.
Um, we can go to the next slide. Thank
you. I'm only showing this just so that
you get an idea um and why it's so
important um that we are able to partner
um with the city of Lancaster because it
took 20 sources of funds to be able to
fund College Awan. Um the total
development cost was $22,817,000
to build those 64 units. Um and uh you
know every dollar that we get in that
helps fund one of our projects is
absolutely critical. And so we're really
grateful for the partnership that we had
on college a one and would like to see
that continued throughout.
Okay, we can skip. So college a phase
two um 49 apartments. It'll be a mix of
studio which is a little different for
us. Um efficiency one and two-bedroom
apartments um 11 apartments will be set
aside for um folks who are experiencing
or at risk of experiencing homelessness.
Um the other thing that is really
exciting for us here is that even we're
going to have 49 apartments, but we've
also partnered with Magro House and uh
the folks at Magro House are working
with us. They're going to take one floor
of the Delt um and we'll take the top
two and a smidge floors. Um and uh Magro
House will be providing roughly 19 uh
apartments for single parents who are uh
looking to continue and further their
education. And so, um, it's, you know,
getting this building up and running is
not just the 49 apartments, but it's
also a larger help to the community by
including, um, this wonderful
partnership with Magro House. Um,
I think that's that's pretty much all
you need there. And again, if we can
switch sides again, I would just say,
you know, the sources um, you know,
every dollar is critical. Um, we have a
few less sources here, but this building
is already existing. We're not building
from scratch. Uh and so on we'll be
using the Delt building. It will not be
taken down. We'll be uh converting the
interior to function uh for apartments
and and residential living. But our
total development costs at this
particular time are $19,743,000
for phase two.
And we can we can skip to the next one.
Thank you. And this is college ad phase
three. This is what is over on Marietta
Avenue. Um and so you kind of get a
little bit of a look here. This one's a
little different than what we've been
providing and will be a little smaller
than the other buildings that we've been
looking at. Um, in the top right hand
corner is where we're looking at where
the building would sit. Um, and then
we're estimating probably somewhere in
the neighborhood of 40 to 50 apartments
in that location. Uh, they would be a
mix of one to two-bedroom apartments. It
would additionally be family housing
again. Um and we would reserve um for
all households uh earning between um 20
and 60% of the area median income in the
Lancaster area. Um and of course just
like we would do with phase one and two,
it would be architecturally compatible
with the neighborhood. And so this is in
early stages of development, so things
can potentially change, but um really
excited about the opportunity to be able
to kind of close this one out and bring
all three communities to Lancaster over
there on the College Avenue area.
and we can go to the next one. Thank
you. Um and so here is uh proposed
sources. Um and so this one we're
anticipating again a little bit smaller
building, but we would anticipate the
total development cost would be about
$19 million. So between all three
buildings, the investment into the
community here is, you know, over $60
million. And we're really excited um to
be able to uh bring all of that um
infrastructure and um resources and
services uh to the West End
neighborhood.
Okay, my timeline, we can switch to the
next one. Um so phase one, as I
mentioned earlier, is complete. Phase
two, we submitted our tax credit
application to the Pennsylvania Housing
Finance Agency in uh February of this
year. and um we can keep our fingers
crossed and hope we're anticipating
hearing about awards in October and so
um really excited about hearing what
happens there. Um I did not mention it
in the slides but we have a wonderful
partnership with um LGH and um PHFA uh
the Pennsylvania Housing Finance Agency
is very excited about that partnership.
Um and so we're really excited to be
able to work with the group over there.
Um, we would look to, if we get the
award, um, then we would be looking to
close and begin construction at the end
of 2026. That's for phase two. Um, and
be fully leased up and operational in
2028.
Um, and so, uh, phase three, uh, which
is over on Marietta, which we've been
talking about, um, we would look to
submit an application early in 2027.
Typically, Pennsylvania Housing Finance
Agency has applications due Q1 and so we
would anticipate submitting it then and
then before the end of the year hearing
about that award there um and then fully
occupied and leased and functional by um
the summer of 2030. So just keeping all
of the construction and all of the
pieces moving um to get us to the end of
all three phases here. And that's
basically my presentation. Um I do have
a couple pictures if you're interested.
We did a meet and greet with our board
of directors. Um, if you want to switch
to the next slide. We did a meet and
greet with our board of directors and
the residents there. So, um, everybody
got to meet um, everybody. We had pizza,
we played some get to know you games and
it was a really wonderful event and, um,
so these are some of the residents and
some of our board members um, at College
A1. And I would like to, you know, be
available if you have any questions, do
my best to answer them.
>> Kim, thank you so much for your
presentation this evening. I want to
just clarify um and I appreciate the
back information because I think it's
incredible how much goes into these
projects and it's worth reiterating
again and again like how many funding
sources this takes, how many people it
requires to do this work um and how much
time it takes to do it.
>> Um for the resolution and the
application then that is in front of us
this evening. Uh this would be for
specifically phase
>> three. Um and you showed us sort of like
that funding stack for phase three. Can
you tell us how much of that is
considered committed at this point?
>> So um the only thing that's committed is
a contribution that we already have in
hand which is from Steinman. Okay. And
so we have that and I believe there is a
um an HDC uh portion and that is also
committed. Those are our first two
pieces in
>> and that's why the timeline is the way
it is.
>> That's why it is. Yep. takes that long
to build the capital stack. Yes,
>> that is correct. Okay. I wanted to make
sure we uh laid that out very clearly.
>> Absolutely.
>> Terrific. Thank you for your
presentation. Uh I'll take any council
comments or questions,
>> Council Craig.
>> I just have a comment that um
>> this is incredible.
>> Yeah,
>> it really is incredible,
>> you know, to to be here from the
beginning when it was a thought and see
the whole process
>> follow through. Um, I can't wait to see
the whole thing done.
>> Yeah,
>> it'll be great.
>> Thank you. Thank you. Additional
comments from council.
>> And I'll just remind before we take uh
comments from the public that again,
these applications are going uh to the
state. It's not funding that
unfortunately the city has, but it is
state gaming funds that entities can
apply for uh with municipal support. Um,
so I'll take any comments on the
resolution.
>> I think it's a great thing to see.
>> Oh, I'm sorry. I did not clarify this
fully and there's some other folks
coming. But, uh, to make comment, just
come right on up to this microphone and
that helps us be heard on in the room
and both on the recording online. So, if
you'd like to make comment, go right on
up and please begin with your name and
your block of residence. Good evening.
>> Good evening. Tony Dastra, 700 block of
New Holland Avenue. Um,
not trying to say anything to freak
anybody out. It's that this is a genuine
question. Um, I'm hearing that the HUD
director, Scott Turner, might be making
a push to, uh, kick people out of their
housing situations, uh, who are in
affordable housing programs like the
ones offered here. Um, just what what
can we kind of expect for existing
residents who might be undocumented
uh, in your facilities? Um, I'm looking
forward to the project as it is. Um, so
I don't want to like come at you too
much because like you're just one small
piece of everything we need to do.
>> Um, but do you have any insight to what
I'm talking about and what we might be
able to expect?
>> So I think I hear two questions. Uh, is
the first question uh with the changes
that are happening at HUD uh decreased
funding at HUD and things like that that
we're concerned that people might lose
housing. Is that the first question? And
then is the second piece about um the
residents who are actually living there
and their status as residents. Is that
the second question?
>> Yes. I mean I already know that
decreases in funding are going to affect
the affordable housing opportunities. My
question is more just if if there are
people who are currently in your housing
uh units that are undocumented with
these other changes at HUD, not funding
but more philosophical changes. Um, do
people need to be concerned about
whether they can stay in your units just
because I know that you are dependent on
funding streams and kind of these odd,
in my opinion, unnecessary decrees. But
>> um, so what I would say first is that
um, um, the properties that we're
talking about here are funded through a
program called the lowincome housing tax
credit program. You might see it as
LIHTC.
Um, and that program basically funds up
front. It's a public private
partnership. So, we get tax credits from
the Pennsylvania Housing Finance Agency
and then we sell those tax credits to
big investors that put up big money. So,
we actually don't receive a ton of HUD
money into these deals. Okay. Um,
they're predominantly um paid for
through the low-inccome housing tax
credit program and as you look through
the capital stack, a lot of private
foundations and things like that. Um,
and so I'm not home money is important.
I want to make sure I say that. I think
I was quoted in the newspaper the other
day with that. Home money is incredibly
important and critical to uh our ability
to be able to build affordable housing.
And home money does come trickles down
from the HUD budget. And so, you know,
we're kind of watching how things are
going there. But at this particular
moment, um, there's nothing that would
do that. The residents that live there
pay their income pay pay their rent
based on their income. So there's no
>> no worry about that.
>> No worry about that. The other thing I
would say is that we have to um
completely certify our residents before
they move in. And so um all the
residents that live there um have proven
that you know that they're allowed to be
here.
>> Okay. Thank you.
>> Any additional comments from the public?
>> Good evening.
>> Good evening. Jose Nunes Hu 100 block of
South Queen Street. I would like to
congratulate your program. Um that's
definitely something that as a
commissioner and many of the other
commissioners throughout the
Commonwealth have advocated for
affordable housing. So it is great to
see that Lancaster city and and are are
definitely doing that because that we
have definitely we have recognized
there's a housing shortage in the
Commonwealth. I mean the common is
growing but when it comes to housing and
housing opportunity for people who don't
have the opportunity to live somewhere
it's not there. So I do want to go
graduate program would like to see if I
could get a copy or somehow we could
connect. So maybe we could uh bring a
couple of the commissioners and see how
we all work together. But I think I want
to go graduate program. We definitely
definitely there is a housing shortage
and right now I see you're meeting the
needs at least in our in our city and in
our counties for people that need that
place to live.
>> So thank you.
>> Thank you. Thank you.
>> Thank you. Any further comments on the
public for the resolution?
>> Good evening.
>> Hi, good afternoon. Nancy Mangan Garden.
I want to say congratulations to the her
too and to the city and to the
administration for all these apartments
because it's not a lot but 100 and
something apartments that are coming up
on that project is amazing and then we
are not building nothing new so why are
we using the buildings that's amazing
guys as well so congratulations on that
measurement
>> thank you
any further comments from the public on
the resolution Hearing
none. Mr. Harris,
>> Mr. Men,
>> I.
>> Mr. Roya,
>> Mr. Cle,
>> I,
>> Miss Craig,
>> Miss Diaz,
>> I,
>> and President Baker,
>> I. Thank you. Thanks, guys. Thank you
very much.
Perfect.
And as my old apparently and new agenda
tells us, we've reached the end of our
legislative agenda this evening. Uh
which will take us to our second public
comment period. Uh that comment period
is open for items that were not on the
agenda. Again, duration of comments is
limited to three minutes per speaker and
please begin with your name and block of
residence for the meeting record. If
anyone wishes to make public comment at
this time, please come to the
microphone.
Thank you.
>> Thank you very much.
Good evening.
>> Good evening. Uh you you know me. I'm
Frank Archolio
uh from uh Old Trinity Place and uh I'm
the one who is appealing the the uh data
center ruling uh by the zoning uh
officer in back in February calling a
data center a warehouse. uh you um you
on the council have requested a process
to go through
um President Bay, I don't think you
started my time.
>> Well, thank you.
>> Not to cut myself short, but
>> it's a little finicky, but keep going.
You're you're good. Thank you. Um but
but in any case um you have requested
the beginning of a process that I
believe is its next step is that you're
going to look at a draft ordinance on
October 6th. Uh that's what I
understand. But uh but what I have here
for you is um something that could
shortcut the process which is kind of
our idea of what a draft ordinance would
be uh to regulate data centers.
First thing let me talk about what a
data center is. A data center is a
facility whose primary purpose is the
centralized storage, processing,
management or dissemination of digital
data, information or applications. This
includes but is not limited to server
farms, cloud computing hubs, collocation
centers, and telecommun communication
switching hubs. Data centers typically
house large-scale computer systems and
supporting infrastructure such as backup
generators, cooling systems, and
uninterruptible power supplies. That
does not sound like a warehouse to me. I
have to say the uses that we would uh uh
suggest are conditional uses uh for both
the C3, CM, and SM. All three of those
uh uh zones.
What would be some of the restrictions?
Well, uh, going to page three, energy
use. Data centers shall operate on 100%
renewable energy for all electrical and
cooling needs, either through on-site
generation or verifiable power purchase
agreements. Backup generators should
meet or exceed EPA tier 4 final
admission standards. And the facility
should not require upgrades to the grid,
the municipal electric distri
distribution infrastructure, unless all
those upgrades are fully paid for by the
applicant. Water and cooling systems.
I'll only go over the first provision.
All water used for cooling operations or
operations shall be non-potable and all
discharges shall be treated to a level
equal or better than the affluent
standard of the city.
Uh going on to I'm doing a this a little
bit out of order. Uh noise emissions
should not exceed 50 dB at any property
line and uh a period of
publicformational meeting shall be held.
Uh the city may require a community
benefits agreement as part of it. And
then finally uh a document uh
decommissioning plan shall outline
procedures for the safe removal of ser
server infrastructure, hazardous
materials, batteries, electronic waste,
all that kind of stuff backed up by uh
substantial performance bond in case uh
they decide that the data center glut
has gotten uh hold and they just want to
throw the keys up on the roof and uh
leave us to clean it up. Those those are
uh suggested ordinance uh capable of uh
Mr. Dastra and others that we would like
to be considered as part of the ultimate
uh zoning uh ordinance amendment for
data centers. Thank you.
>> Thank you very much, Mr. Aolio.
>> Are there any additional comments for
this period?
Tony Dastra, 700 block of New Holland
Avenue. Uh, I don't think I need to beat
a dead horse. I second what Mr. Arolio
uh is saying about the data centers and
regulation.
Uh, but two separate things. I'll tie it
to some of the discussion tonight. Uh I
am concerned about the soundness of
Lanster city government right now. Uh
through I don't know what it is with
2024 but between the tech issues here
and uh agenda posting issues there have
been a variety of city government
meetings canceled or postponed including
yesterday's zoning hearing board which
is not good for the productivity of the
city especially to any of the developers
who may have been there yesterday for
whatever decisions. Uh but I also
recognize those things need to be
delayed when sunshine law isn't met
because you open a door to reverse
decisions. Uh so that's a frustration I
have. But to talk to about something
separately kind of related to uh
resolution 63 up there. The affordable
housing situation in Lancaster is crazy.
The housing situation in Langster is
crazy. And that project alone is not
enough. We need to do more, not just in
terms of construction of units, but the
regulation of existing units. We need
rent control in Lancaster City for
existing units to make sure people can
remain in their homes, whether that be
their apartment building or a house they
are renting.
It is scary for people to have to go to
the end of their lease and they're not
sure if they're going to see an
increase, not because the landlord has
invested in their properties, but
because the other surrounding rents have
gotten high on the new units, which is
pushing up the price of the old units
that have no improvements done to them.
We need practical I'm not out here
saying that we should be doing blind
rent control policy. Every single unit
just is stuck where it's at. But we need
reasonable investment to accompany the
increases that people experience. I
think it is time, I know it's time for
Lanster City to start having
conversation and enacting rent control.
The people desperately need it and I
feel that talk to the priorities of
strong neighborhoods, safe places,
sustainable economy because the most
dire economic situation is the household
and sound government. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
Are there any additional comments for
this period?
Right. Hearing none, we will close the
second public comment period. I thank
everyone. Uh that will take us to the
report of the mayor, Mayor Sarra.
>> I have no additional report this
evening. Thank you.
>> Thank you. Uh the next item on our
agenda is the report of president of
council. I don't have anything
additional besides again to remind folks
to come out to the Hispanic Heritage
Festival on October 4th. Hopefully,
we'll have lovely weather and not
whatever is happening outside right now.
Uh and it'll be a great celebration. So,
thank you. Are there any uh the next
item is council comments. Are there any
council comments this evening?
Right. Hearing none and having reached
the end of our agenda, I'll hear a
motion to adjurnn.
>> Motion to adjurnn.
>> Second.
>> Have a motion and a second. And all in
faith.